Guide to the Joseph M. Scammell papers, 1910-1952 and undated RL.11846
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph M. Scammell papers
1910-1952 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11846
14 Linear Feet 34 boxes; 2 oversize folders
Joseph M. Scammell (1888-1953) was a military historian, author, and educator. His papers comprise two main groups: military history education materials in the form of lectures, curricula, and other course materials, and published and unpublished writings by Scammell and others, chiefly articles and lectures on international and U.S. military history from Classical Greece to World War II. There are also files of personal and professional correspondence, printed materials such as clippings, maps, and diaries. Scrapbooks contain articles on World War II campaigns in Britain, Germany, Latin America, and Turkey.
Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, Military Education Materials, Printed Materials, Scrapbooks and Clippings, and Diaries and Other Papers.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph M. Scammell was a military historian, author, and educator. He was an alumnus of the California University system (1915), also serving as a teaching fellow and instructor from 1915-1919. He served as infantry captain in World War I, and in 1917 was stationed at Fort Sill, Oklahoma. After the war he was a member of the Army Reserve (Officers Reserve Corps, O.R.C.). He studied military history at Oxford, 1923-1924, and served in the National Guard Bureau from 1931-1935. From 1936-1939 Scammell was a Field Supervisor for Military Records for the National Historical Records Survey.
From the 1930s to the late 1940s he taught military history at the following schools: Command and General Staff School and the General Service Schools, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas; Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia; and the School of Military Government, Charlottesville, Virginia, and the Army Industrial College, Washington, D.C., where in 1945 he was appointed as Historical Officer, Civil Affairs Division.
Scammell's articles on military history appeared mainly in military periodicals in the United States and abroad, including in the Infantry Journal, United States Naval Institute Proceedings, Army Quarterly, and North American Review.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Joseph M. Scammell papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1971 and 1985.
Scope and Contents
The papers of military historian and educator Joseph M. Scammell comprise two main groups: military history education materials in the form of curricula, lectures, student assignments, and other course materials, and writings by Scammell and others, chiefly typed and handwritten manuscripts and published articles on international and U.S. military history from the Greeks to World War II. There are also smaller amounts of personal and professional correspondence, including letters from editors, printed materials, maps, and clippings. Scrapbooks in the Clippings Series contain articles on World War II campaigns in Britain, Germany, Latin America, and Turkey.
United States. Army -- History; Military education -- United States; Military historians -- United States; Military history, Ancient -- Historiography; Military history, Modern -- 20th century -- Historiography; Military history -- Study and teaching -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns; Europe -- History, Military; United States -- History, Military; Diaries; Scrapbooks
- Correspondence, 1916-1952; 8 folders
  - 1916, June-1952, October (Box 1)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 1)
- Writings and Speeches, circa 1920s-1940s
  - ABC's of War - Art of Command According to Xenophon (Box 2)
  - Augean Stables of the Law - Carleton as a Commander (Box 2)
  - Carnegie - Escape of the Goeben and Breslau (Box 2)
  - Europe in Arms - Gold, Iron Power, Women, and War (Box 3)
  - Grand Catalan Company - Greek Mercenaries and the Citizen Soldier (Box 3)
  - Guam - How Come? - Mesilla and San Augustine (Box 3)
  - Military Education and Indoctrination - "My Friend Says..." (Box 3)
  - Military Government: Algiers, 1830-1834 - Historical Summary of Allied Military Government and Civil Affairs (Box 3)
  - Military Government during the Napoleonic Wars - Military Government in the Philippines (Box 4)
  - Military Government of Guam-Sicily, 1806-1913 (Box 4)
  - Sir John Moore - Use of Military Force and Civil Police in Occupied and Liberated Territories (Box 4)
  - Napoleon's Staff - Of Prophecies (Box 4)
  - Old Antiquarian's Corner - Orange Fleet (Box 4)
  - Organization and Procedure for Mobilization Planning - Pearl Harbor (Box 5)
  - Socrates and the Art of War - Sun-Tsu's Estimate of the Situation (Box 5)
  - The Sword of the Lord and of Gideon - University Students and War (Box 5)
  - Waging War - We Americans and the Moros of Lanao (Box 5)
  - What the Army Never Learns - William Need: Soldier Prophet (Box 5)
  - Phantom Army - Soldier Seen (Box 5)
  - Six Wise Saws and Modern Instances - Yankee Ward (Box 6)
  - Untitled writings, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Military Education Materials, 1919-1940s
  - Army Industrial College, 1944-1946 and undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Army Industrial College, Scrapbook 2, 1940s; 2 folders, 1 volume (Box 7)
  - Command and General Staff School, Ft. Leavenworth, Kansas, 1936-1943 July (Box 7)
  - Command and General Staff School, Ft. Leavenworth, Kansas, 1943 August and undated (Box 8)
  - General Services School, Ft. Leavenworth, Kansas, 1919-1933; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Infantry School, Ft. Benning, Georgia, 1932-1933 and undated (Box 8)
  - Maps, undated (Box 8)
  - School of Military Government, 1942, February 15-1943, Jan. 21 (Box 8)
  - School of Military Government, 1940s; 4 folders, 1 volume (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville, Virginia, 1943 and undated (Box 9)
  - School of Military Government, 1944-1945 (Box 10)
  - The Army Industrial College - Outline of Military Interest of the Classics (Box 10)
  - Old Records in a New War - A Suggested Plan for a Course of Instruction in War Studies (Box 10)
  - The Tactics of the Byzantine Army - The Widening Concept of Military History (Box 10)
- Printed Materials, 1910 June-1947 April
  - 1910, June-1942, July, 7 folders (Box 11)
  - 1943, February-1947, Apr., n.d., 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Maps, 431 BC-1922 and undated (Box 12)
  - Maps, 1861-1940s and undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Maps, 1883-1918 and undated (Oversize-folder 2)
- Scrapbooks and Clippings, 1921-1945 and undated
  - Clippings, 1940-1945 and undated (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1932-1942; 6 folders (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1941-1942; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1921-1922; 2 folders (Box 15)
- Other Papers and Diaries, 1926-1950 and undated
  - General papers, 1926-1950 and undated (Box 15)
  - Diaries, 1920s (Box 15)
  - Diaries, 1931-1932 (Box 15)
  - Papers, undated (Box 34)
    Scope and Contents
    This box has not been examined by library staff during the creation of this inventory.
  - Diaries, 1935 (Box 15)
- Index Cards
  - Subject cards (Box 16)
    This box contains loose and boxed index cards pertaining to various subjects. Loose note cards include subject material such as Roman armies, weapons, and troops. Also includes information labeled Byzantine Rome. The boxed note cards contain bibliography cards.
  - Subject cards (Box 17)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards. The separate categories are titled according to subjects such as camps, cavalry, and equipment. The categories are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Titles cards (Box 18)
    This box is labeled "Titles" and contains all sub-grouped note cards. The category titles are either subjects, such as Titans and Rivers, or letters, such as TYR, KOR, and IRON. The categories are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Category titles (Box 19)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with category titles such as War of Titans, Magic, 121, and DRU. These categories are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Quotes, propaganda, notes (Box 20)
    This box contains note cards grouped in three different ways. Some are separately boxed and are mostly quotes and propaganda. There are some category titles such as Right, Time, and Prevention. Other note cards are grouped together but have no labels. These contain quotes, facts, and some French. The rest of the note cards in this box are loose and have some sub-titles. These are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Subject cards (Box 21)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with category titles such as Theseus, Aegeus, and Europe. They are mostly research notes and quotes, and are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Strategies and maxims, subjects, and quotes (Box 22)
    This box contains some separately boxed note cards with strategies and maxims. There are also some sub-grouped note cards with titles such as French Doctrine, and Clausewitz. These categories are not arranged alphabetically. There is also an unlabeled group which contains quotes and dates.
  - Research notes, quotes (Box 23)
    This box contains separately boxed note cards with sub-titles and information which appears to be research notes and quotes. There are also some sub-grouped note cards containing quotes, facts, notes, and maps. Most sub-titles pertain to the late eighteenth century such as the Campaign of 1796 in Italy. These categories are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Research notes (Box 24)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with titles which are not arranged alphabetically. The information includes campaigns, war facts from different centuries (530-1900s), a map, and library home use slips.
  - Subject cards (Box 25)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with category titles such as Axis, Invasion, and Naval War. These categories are not arranged alphabetically. The information includes quotes, policies, facts, and library home use slips.
  - Research notes (Box 26)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards of research notes including quotes and facts.
  - Subject cards - Greece and Persia (Box 27)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with categories such as Persian Wars, and tactics (morale, training, stategy, etc.). Most of this box pertains to Greece and Persia. The categories are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Subject cards (Box 28)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with detailed sub-titles such as GI Mobilization, Recruiting, and Troop Movements, and different geographical areas such as Germany, Western Europe, and China. These categories are not arranged alphabetically. This box also contains library home use slips, printed clippings, and maps.
  - Research notes (Box 29)
    This box contains loose note cards with no sub-titles. The information includes quotes and some written in French.
  - Research notes (Box 30)
    This box contains a section of separately grouped note cards including a chronological account of the 1840s. The rest of the note cards are sub-grouped with category titles such as Siskiyou Co., and Addresses, but are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Subject cards (Box 31)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards with category titles such as Armed Forces, Duty, and Policy. These categories are not arranged alphabetically.
  - Chronological and subject cards (Box 32)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards which span the sixth century to the fifteenth century and are sub-titled Rome, Byzantine, Constantine, Turks, etc. These categories are not arranged alphabetically. The information mostly consists of research notes including quotes and dates.
  - Subject cards (Box 33)
    This box contains all sub-grouped note cards pertaining to education, the eighteenth century, Napoleon, and other topics. The box also contains library home use slips and a map. Categories are not arranged alphabetically.